In this lesson, we're going to be learning about type aliases in TypeScript, so type aliases
let us give a name to a type, which makes our code cleaner, reasonable, and much easier
to understand.
Type aliases are used pretty much everywhere in real TypeScript projects, especially when
working with objects, unions, and complex data structures.
So let's demonstrate by starting off with a problem.
Sometimes we repeat our same type over and over again.
Let's have a user of one, and we have ID number, name string.
Let's create another user type, let's call it user two, and maybe even have user three.
Now, we can see that we're just repeating the same object structure over and over again,
which is going to quickly become messy, as well as making its heart maintain.
So a type alias allows us to create a custom name for the type.
What we can do instead is we can come to here and we can create a type for this particular
user shape, so we can do type user, and then we can define the properties ID number, name
equals string, and we saw this briefly in the previous lesson how we use this.
Now what we can do of course is we can now create objects of that given type, so we can
do let's user one equals the user one is a type of user, and then we can create the properties
to ID one, name equals Alice.
And then we can come and do the second user, user two is of type user, specify the ID,
ID of two, name is Bob.
So now our code becomes so much cleaner and much easier to update.
Now, the structure changes at all on this user, we want to perhaps put a phone number
or something, then we can just do it on our type, rather than having to do it multiple
times.
These aliases don't just change behavior, but they add meaning and clarity to our code.
Now, type aliases really come into the own when we're working with union types.
This is remove the code here and do an example.
So we have a type status, and this might be something like success with the pipe symbol,
maybe error, pipe symbol, and then loading for example, so three separate statuses.
Now, this limits our values to the specific set, making our code much safer.
Now, we can define and an actual instance of that by doing a let current status is of
our type status.
Now, we just set our value say to success, we try and set it as something else, perhaps
like done, for example, then we're going to get an error because it's not one of those
three values.
We can also use type aliases to describe function shapes.
So let's come to here and do an example.
If we do type of add, and we say A number, and we have another B number, now we can just
simply use the arrow, and we can say it is of type or returns number.
So we can do type add, and then we need to do brackets, and we say the first parameter
is A, and that's a number, then we have a parameter B, which is also a number, and then
we can simply use this arrow shortcut to define the return type of this function, and say
it returns a number.
Now we can actually define the implementation of that function, we can do const say add numbers,
we say it's of type add, so that means it has two parameters, let's say x and y, and now
we create the actual implementation of that function, and because we're adding numbers
together, we might say it's x plus y, and we can do another one, for example, subtract
numbers, this is our function add, while adds a really silly name, but let's say you take
two numbers, and that would be x minus y, also particularly good naming there, but you
can see the point, you can see xy, and it say the actual, the product of x minus y, we
shouldn't really call that add, but you can see the point here, where we can actually
then define the implementation, by using the type here.
Type aliases can also describe more complex structures, let's have a type of address, this
has a street, of type string, a city, of type string, and we might have another type
of user profile, an ID, which is number, a name, but more importantly, we can have an address,
which is going to reuse our address type at this, but this structure allows us to help
break these structures into much more smaller and reasonable pieces, so we have a simple
address here, defining on our user profile, and we can go as many levels as we want.
So let's have a summary of type aliases, so these gives us a name, so our types, it allows
us to improve readability and reuse, it allows us to work with objects, unions, functions,
and primitives, and they are very important because they are core building block in
TypeScript.